A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Printed Material, RG 8 FA1802
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Printed Material, RG 8
1954-2020
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation
FA1802
6.19 Cubic Feet (14 containers)
Arrangement
Record Group 8, Printed Material is divided into four series:
Series 1: Newsletters
Series 2: Articles and Clippings
Series 3: Publications
Series 4: Miscellaneous
Scope and Contents
Record Group 8 contains newsletters, articles, clippings, publications, and posters related to the work of the Knight Foundation. This series includes both internal and external communications created by the Knight Foundation as well as secondary sources that cover philanthropy, grants/grantees, and various programs and initiatives.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Material less than 10 years old is restricted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Philanthropy; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States
- Newsletters, 1989-2017; 1; 1.52 Cubic Feet 4 letter document boxes
  Arrangement
  Chronological by type of newsletter.
  Scope and Contents
  The newsletters contain information about grant programs, officers, trustees, staff changes, the status of various initiatives, and interesting stories about Knight Foundation grants/grantees.
  - Knight Foundation Newsletter, 1989 October-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1-8, 10-15)
    General
    Knight File Number - 264
    Newsletter distributed to grantees and other interested parties; issued quarterly from October, 1989 until 1998 (Volumes 1-38). Includes features on grants awarded, initiatives, staff news, trustee news, and awards.
  - Inside Knight Foundation, 1996 June-August (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 263
    Occasional newsletter written for advisors and committee members. Initiated 6/96, only volumes 1-2 were written. Articles include staff changes, committee changes, board member news, publications and meeting dates.
  - Knight News (Employee Newsletter), 1998 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Knight File Number - 1056
    Knight News (employee newsletter) was created in February 1998 to inform employees regarding their benefits, current events, and issues of office life. Included are articles on Section 125 Spending Accounts, Dental Plan, Defined Contribution Plan, Health and Life Insurance, personal benefits statements, Book Club, Records Day, Corporate Run, Family Outing, Employee Assistance Plan (EAP), Education Assistance.
  - Knight Foundation Newsletter, 1999-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1-10)
    Newsletter distributed to grantees and other interested parties; issued quarterly from 1999 until Fall 2001 (Volumes 39-50). Includes features on grants awarded, initiatives, staff news, trustee news, and awards.
  - News@Knight, 2002-2003 October (Box 2, Folder 11-13)
    Knight File Number - 2381
    News@Knight, quarterly publication of the Knight Foundation, is aimed at grantees and other interested parties. Starting with Issue No. 51, the Knight Foundation Newsletter had a new look and name. More space was devoted to developments in Journalism Initiatives and Community Partners programs. Box 2 contains Issues 51-58.
  - News@Knight, 2004-2006 July (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
    Knight File Number - 2695
    News@Knight, quarterly publication of the Knight Foundation, is aimed at grantees and other interested parties. Box 3 starts with Issue No. 59, Winter 2004. The last issue published was No. 68, Spring/Summer 2006.
  - Working@Knight, 2001 April 4-2007 August (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 2730
    Working@Knight is an electronic newsletter sent to Knight Foundation Advisers and other interested parties to keep them informed of notable grants and Knight Foundation news. The file contains printed versions of the e-newletter, printed on a monthly basis.
  - KnightNews (monthly e-newsletter), 2008 July 3 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 4424
    KnightNews is a monthly e-newsletter update on the "experimentation and innovation underway at Knight Foundation."
  - Knight Arts Update, 2009 November 16-2016 June 27 (Box 3, Folder 11-14)
    Knight File Number - 4605
    The newsletter, published weekly only on the Knight Arts Blog, provides updates on the South Florida Arts community. There are gaps in this collection from June 2011 to June 2013. Also starting in 2013, the blog featured arts across all of KF's communities. (4 folders)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted - Open in 2027.
  - Community Information Needs, 2010 January 13 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Knight File Number - 4725
    The newsletter, published only online at www.informationneeds.org serves to inform the public on resources available to Communities as part of the Community Information Needs project. One issue (1/13/2010) lists the winners of the second Knight Community Information Challenge.
  - Knight News - Trustees Edition, 2010 May-2011 May (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Knight File Number - 4759
    Monthly e-newsletter, published online for KF trustees, provides information on KF staff, grants, awards, and current news. Starting in November 2010, the online addition was supplemented with a printed abstract for distribution to trustees.
  - Comms Weekly, 2013 July-2017 July (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
    Knight File Number - 5224
    Announcement of a new e-newsletter, Comms Weekly, distributed to KF staff by Andrew Sherry, VP of Communications. Email presents events coming up with a communications component, as well as a snapshot of press highlights and social media performance from the week before. Some weeks, information on the launching of the new initiative, Knight News Challenge: Health, are included. That challenge is being led by Matt Haggman and John Bracken. The September 16, 2013 issue includes information on the Detroit Knight Arts Challenge Awards. Also included is the announcement of the opening of the Perez Art Museum, which includes a John S. and James L. Knight Plaza. Starting in July 2016, Comms Weekly changed formats and title to Comms Monthly which was published once a month. 5 folders
    Restricted - Open in 2028.
  - Fluxx Quarterly Update, 2013 August 23-2016 August 22 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 5225
    Announcement of a new e-newsletter, Fluxx Quarterly Update, and a copy of the third quarter update. The updates are intended to inform staff about improvements being made to KF's Fluxx Grants Management System. Also included is a 1st quarter 2014 Update and updates in the form of memos to staff re: new grant form and grantee portal in 2016.
  - Knight's Media Innovation Newsletter, 2015 September 28-2016 July 12 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 5578
    Announcement of a new e-newsletter, Knight's Media Innovation Newsletter (called simply Media Innovation Newsletter by January 2016). This will be a monthly newsletter produced by the Media Innovation team to share what's happening in their world, shine a light on alumni and current grantees, and inform about media and tech events around the country.
  - Knight Enterprise Fund Update, 2016 March 13-2017 March 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 5634
    Announcement of a new e-newsletter, Knight Enterprise Fund Update, a bi-weekly memo to staff featuring portfolio news, job opportunities at start-ups, additions to the funds, and other news of note.
  - @KnightFdn, 2011 September-2017 August 14 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 4947
    Announcement of a new e-newsletter, @KnightFdn, which consists of Tweet-length entries linked back to KnightBlog. Also included is an issue of the e-newsletter. Following a gap of almost two years, "issues" beginning in the summer of 2013 have a new appearance.
- Articles and Clippings, 1954-2015; 2; 2.14 Cubic Feet 4 containers
  Chronological.
  - Clara I. Knight, 1954-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4209
    Number of clippings, mostly from the Akron Beacon Journal, pertaining to Clara Knight, the mother of John and James Knight, and a contributor to the Knight Foundation. The articles refer to her clubs and activities, her family life and background, and her sons and grandsons.
  - "Publisher John S. Knight: The New Breed" - Newsweek cover story, 1995 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4205
    Issue features a portrait of John S. Knight on the cover. Provides background information and features interviews with Knight newsmen. Also mentioned are James L. Knight and Lee Hills. 2 original issues and a color copy.
  - Article on Knight Foundation Student Loans, 1959 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 820
    "Knight Foundation to Aid 11 Students" article from 1959. Publication unknown.
  - Article on Knight Foundation Student Loans, 1963 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 821
    "Six Area Students Win Knight Foundation Loans" article from Akron Beacon Journal, 7/22/63.
  - Article on Knight Foundation Student Loans, 1964 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 822
    "7 Win Knight Scholarships" article from Akron Beacon Journal, 7/1/64.
  - Article on Knight Foundation Student Loans, 1965 August 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 823
    "8 in Area Get Knight Awards" article in Akron Beacon Journal on 8/4/65.
  - Article on Knight Foundation Student Loans, 1966 June 22 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 824
    "Five Given Knight Foundation Grants" article in Akron Beacon Journal, 6/22/66.
  - Article on Grant to Akron Public Library, 1971 October 29-30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 825
    Articles from Akron Beacon Journal: "New Downtown Park is Knight Foundation Gift," and "Knight Foundation Park Gift Makes Everybody Happy."
  - Article on Grant for Public Park in Akron, 1973 August 31 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 826
    Article from Akron Beacon Journal: "Library Trustees Cut Back Proposal for 'People Park.'"
  - "Beryl Knight Leaves $1.9 Million Estate", 1974 August 8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 819
    Article on Beryl Knight Estate, designating KF to take control of interests not included in the estate, has no date (probably Akron-Beacon Journal). Mrs. Beryl Knight died on 8/8/1974.
  - Article on James L. Knight and Knight Foundation, 1981 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Knight File Number - 2206
    Miami Herald article, "Knight elected by foundation; grants awarded" re: Knight's election as chairman of the Knight Foundation, succeeding his brother.
  - Articles on John S. Knight's estate and memorial, Journalism Program at Stanford, 1982 February 24-December 21 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Knight File Number - 830
    Articles on the taxes paid by the estate of John S. Knight, a memorial service for John S. Knight, and the John S. Knight Fellowship Program at Stanford University.
  - Article on John S. Knight, 1983 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Knight File Number - 831
    Akron Beacon Journal article: "Conference Room Dedicated in Miami: Remembering One Man's Indelible Impact."
  - Article on John S. Knight Fellowships for Professional Journalism at Stanford University, 1983 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Knight File Number - 832
    California Publisher article on John S. Knight Fellowships for Professional Journalism at Stanford University: "New Name for Fellowships."
  - Article on James Knight receiving honorary degree from University of Florida, 1984 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Knight File Number - 833
    Article from University of Florida's Communigator on honorary degree given to James L. Knight.
  - Articles on James Knight, grant to University of North Carolina, and death of Mary Ann Knight, 1985 January 7-December 31 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Knight File Number - 834
    Articles on an award to James L. Knight, a grant to the University of North Carolina School of Journalism, and the death of James's wife, Mary Ann Knight.
  - News clipping re: John S. Knight Estate, 1985 April 21 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Knight File Number - 1537
    New York Times article (4/21/1985) titled, "Knight Estate to Leave Millions to Foundation." Part of article is cut off.
  - Article on new trustees, 1987 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Knight File Number - 835
    Akron Beacon Journal article: "New Trustees for Knight Foundation"
  - Article on Knight Foundation in "Knight-Ridder News", 1987 Spring (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Knight File Number - 836
    Spring, 1987 issue of Knight-Ridder News contains articles "The Knight Foundation Reaches out to Your Community," and "Knight Foundation Grants at Work." Includes color photographs of the trustees and grantees.
  - Book Review: Charles Whited's biography of John S. Knight, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Knight File Number - 837
    Reviews of Charles Whited's biography of John S. Knight, "Knight: A Publisher in the Tumultuous Century" by the New York Times Book Review and the Akron Beacon Journal.
  - "Knight Foundation Uses New Wealth from Bequest to Help Liberal Arts Colleges", 1989 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Knight File Number - 1557
    Article in the Chronicle of Higher Education titled, "Knight Foundation Uses New Wealth from Bequest to Help Selected Independent Liberal Arts Colleges."
  - "Newspapers and Literacy:...'that all may read'" - American Newspaper Publishers Association, 1989 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Knight File Number - 1040
    Reference publication on literacy by the American Newspaper Publishers Association (ANPA), "Newspapers and Literacy:... that all may read" Published 7/89, Knight Foundation is listed on page 24, under "Literacy Funding by Major National Newspaper Organizations."
  - Foundation Archives, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Knight File Number - 1617
    Various articles from an unidentified publication about the value of foundation archives.
  - News clipping re: James L. Knight Estate, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Knight File Number - 1538
    Unidentified newspaper article (1991) titled, " Foundation to get the bulk of Knight stock."
  - Articles on Kids Voting Program, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Knight File Number - 838
    Articles from USA Today, The Bradenton Herald, and the Charlotte Observer on the Kids Voting program.
  - The Miami Herald - Hurricane Andrew coverage, 1992 August 25-September 7 (Box 1, Folder 10-22)
    Knight File Number - 2450
    Issues of The Miami Herald newspaper featuring the devastation of Hurricane Andrew and its aftermath. Thirteen issues of the newspaper are included (Folders 1 - 13). Some contain the entire newspaper. Later on, only the first (news) section was saved. Some issues have had articles clipped from them.
  - Chronicle of Philanthropy article: "Bold Knight? Foundation Aims to Shed Obscurity", 1993 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Knight File Number - 839
    Reprint of an article from the Chronicle of Philanthropy: "Bold Knight? Foundation Aims to Shed Obscurity." Includes an interview and photograph of Creed Black.
  - Article on a campaign for the Kenan Institute, 1994 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Knight File Number - 840
    Article from the Raleigh, NC News and Observer: "Kenan Institute Reaches into Southeast Asia." The article mentions that Creed Black of the Knight Foundation spoke at the campaign for the Kenan Institute.
  - Article on various grants, the Knight Commission on Intercollegiate Athletics, etc., 1995, 1995 April 18-June 9 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Knight File Number - 841
    Articles on Lee Hills Hall, the John S. Knight Fellowships at Stanford University, the Oregon Symphony, Knight Scholars at Florida A&M University, Florida Philharmonic, Gallaudet University, Kettering Foundation's Project on Public Life and the Press, the Blue Grass Foundation, and the Knight Commission on Intercollegiate Athletics.
  - American News: Aberdeen Special Edition, 1995 August 6-September 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 2453
    Reprint of a five-part series, Charting Change, which presents an in-depth look at the evolution of the Dakota Midland and what is needed to survive, adapt and thrive in the future.
  - The Charlotte Observer - In-depth Look at the Charlotte Region, 1995 September 17-October 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 2452
    Reprint of a four part series on Charlotte, North Carolina which looks at leadership, growth, workforce and neighborhoods.
  - Article on KF grant to Capital Cultural Center, 1996 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Knight File Number - 842
    Article from the Tallahassee Democrat about the Capital Cultural Center: "Arts Center Shapes Up, Name by Name: The Knight Foundation is Keeping the Ball Rolling with a $1 Million Pledge."
  - Articles on Journalism Education, Fellowship Recipients and the Knight Commission, 1997 April 17-July 11 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Knight File Number - 843
    Article from the Chronicle of Higher Education: "Knight Foundation Uses Grants to Improve Journalism Education." Article from New York Times: "More Than 50 Journalists are Fellowship Recipients." Article from USA Today: "Winning One for the Admissions Office."
  - The Kansas City Star: Money Games Inside the NCAA, 1997 October 5-11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 2456
    Reprint of a six-part series of articles examining NCAA problems and some possible solutions. The Knight Commission on ICA is mentioned.
  - The New York Times - Grand Forks, N.D.: After Flooding, After Fire, Salvaging a Cultural Life, 1997 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 2454
    Article on rebuilding of Grand Forks, North Dakota after devastating fire and floods emphasizes the role of cultural institutions. A Knight Foundation grant to the North Valley Arts Council is mentioned.
  - Grand Forks Herald - River Cities Rising: One Year after the Flood, 1998 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 2455
    Special section commemorates the devastating floods and fires that ravaged Grand Forks, North Dakoka in April 1997.
  - 50th Anniversary of Knight Foundation, 2000 June-2001 June (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Knight File Number - 3847
    Articles in the Akron Beacon Journal and The Miami Herald reporting on the 50th anniversary year celebrations of KF and the community grants made in Akron and Miami in its honor. Hodding Carter, Bud Meyer, Gerald Austen, and Penny McPhee are mentioned. Also included is an article in Editor & Publisher magazine about KF's and the Knight Brothers' gifts to journalism education and causes, "The Helping Hands of Journalism" and a KF ad highlighting its 50th year (3 copies). NOTE: The Akron Beacon Journal article is missing page 1.
  - The New York Times - U.S. Attacked, 2001 September 11 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 2451
    Issue of The New York Times reporting on the destruction of the World Trade Center towers and the attack on the Pentagon.
  - "With RFK in the Delta" by John Carr, 2002 April-May (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Knight File Number - 2050
    This article in the April/May issue of American Heritage magazine was written by journalist John Carr, reporter for the Delta Democrat-Times in 1967 when Hodding Carter was editor and associate publisher. Carter's connection to the visit of Robert F. Kennedy to the delta country in 1967 is mentioned.
  - "Knight Foundation invests more than $2.28 million in Charlotte region in 2001", 2002 March-May (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Knight File Number - 2517
    Article appeared in the Spring 2002 Foundation for the Carolinas' Connections Newsletter. It described the new Community Partners program and quoted Knight liaison, Susan Patterson.
  - "Knight Foundation Awards Knight Center $2.2 Million", 2005 March-May (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Knight File Number - 3305
    Article appeared in the Spring 2005 EJ: A magazine of the Knight Center for Environmental Journalism at Michigan State University. Page 8. The grant, which is the largest in the history if the School of Journalism at MSU, will enable the Knight Center to dramatically expand its programs.
  - Sun Herald Special -"The first 100 Days after Hurricane Katrina", 2005 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4349
    Special section commemorates the devastating hurricane and flooding which destroyed the Gulf Coast of Mississippi and Louisiana in 2005 and emphasizes the rebuilding efforts. (2 copies)
  - "Outsourcing: Where Missions Meet", 2005 September-2006 February (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Knight File Number - 3362
    Article, which appeared in CFQ (Commonfund Quarterly) (Fall 2005/Winter 2006) asked the question, "Should your nonprofit outsource some or all of its investment management function?". KF Trustee, John Rogers, Jr. is quoted in the article explaining KF's reasons for outsourcing its investment management function.
  - "New Executives Put Themselves on Macon's Map", 2005 November-December (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Knight File Number - 3363
    Article appeared in November/December 2005 issue of Address Macon and features Beverly Blake, Community Liaison Program Officer for Georgia. The article mentions her work with the Macon community and KF president, Alberto Ibarguen. Also included in a photo with Blake is Macon resident and KF trustee Beverly Knight Olson. (2 copies)
  - "Beacon Journal Facing Loss of Identity", 2005 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Knight File Number - 3364
    Article copied from the Plain Dealer website. Article, which speculates on the possible sale of the Akron Beacon Journal, mentions KF trustee James Crutchfield and John S. Knight. Also included is a timeline of ABJ from its purchase in 1903 by CL Knight.
  - News coverage of First Amendment Survey, 2005 January 28-March (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Knight File Number - 3380
    Selected articles and clippings on KF's survey of American High School students and the First Amendment.
  - A Tale of Two Cities and the Day They Collided: Miami Noir, 2006 January-February (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Knight File Number - 3616
    Columbia Journalism Review article (Jan/Feb 2006 issue) by Tom Austin about the fallout from the suicide of Miami commissioner Art Teele in the lobby of the Miami Herald. Mentioned in the article is the Knight Foundation, Alvah Chapman, Hodding Carter, Alberto Ibarguen and Rod Petrey.
  - Clippings, 2007 May-December (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4207
    Five clippings: 1) Symphony magazine, May-June 2007 "The Knight's Roundtable: Insider reflections on the decade-long Magic of Music Initiative and its impact on the orchestra world." 2) New York Times: May 10, 2007 - "Telling Bogus From True: A Class in Reading News" about KF-sponsored program at SUNY - Stony Brook. Eric Newton is quoted in article. 3) Georgia Informer: "Housing Made Affordable in the City of Macon", September, 2007 re: redevelopment of Beall's Hill with help of a grant from the Knight Foundation. Beverly Blake is mentioned. 4) Miami Herald: "Killers stalk Latin American journalists with impunity", October 15, 2007 re: a Knight Foundation grant to IAPA's impunity project to extend the project. Alberto Ibarguen is mentioned. 5) The Dell & Cannon; A Ransom Everglades School Publication, "Breakthrough receives $3.25 million from Knight Foundation to Expand in Miami", December 2007 re: Knight Foundation grant to Breakthrough Miami to extend its academic enrichment and advancement program for middle and high school students in Miami. Alberto Ibarguen is mentioned.
  - Clippings, 2008 March 4-October 17 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4326